So this right here
هذه الصورة هنا
is the tiny village of Elle, close to Lista.
تمثل قرية "يلة" الصغيرة، الواقعة قرب ليستا.
It's right at the southernmost tip of Norway.
في أقصى جنوب النرويج.
And on January 2 this year,
في يوم 2 يناير من هذه السنة،
an elderly guy who lives in the village,
خرج عجوز يعيش في القرية
he went out to see what was cast ashore
ليرى ما ألقته المياه إلى الشاطئ
during a recent storm.
بعد العاصفة الأخيرة.
And on a patch of grass right next to the water's edge,
فوجد على رقعة من الحشيش، أمام حافة المياه،
he found a wetsuit.
بدلة غوص.
It was grey and black, and he thought it looked cheap.
كانت ذات لون رمادي وأسود، وبدت له رخيصة الثمن.
Out of each leg of the wetsuit
وبرزت من رجلي البدلة
there were sticking two white bones.
عظمتين بيضاء اللون.
It was clearly the remains of a human being.
وكان من الواضح أنها بقايا إنسان.
And usually, in Norway, dead people are identified quickly.
في النرويج، عادة ما يتم تحديد هوية الموتى سريعا.
So the police started searching
فبدأت الشرطة البحث
through missing reports from the local area,
بين عداد المفقودين على الصعيد المحلي،
national missing reports,
والصعيد الوطني،
and looked for accidents with a possible connection.
والبحث عن حوادث قد تكون مرتبطة.
They found nothing.
لكن لم يجدوا أي شيء.
So they ran a DNA profile,
فقاموا بتحليل الحمض النووي،
and they started searching internationally through Interpol.
و إجراء تحقيقا دوليا عبر الأنتربول.
Nothing.
لا شيء.
This was a person that nobody seemed to be missing.
يبدو أنه شخص لم يفتقده أحد.
It was an invisible life heading for a nameless grave.
حياة غير مرئية في إتجاه قبر لا يحمل إسما.
But then, after a month,
لكن بعد شهر،
the police in Norway got a message from the police in the Netherlands.
تلقت الشرطة بالنرويج رسالة من الشرطة الهولندية.
A couple of months earlier, they had found a body,
بضعة أشهر من قبل، وجدوا جثة أيضا،
in an identical wetsuit, and they had no idea who this person was.
في بذلة مشابهة، و لم يكن لديهم أي فكرة عمن كان ذلك الشخص.
But the police in the Netherlands managed to trace the wetsuit
لكن تمكنت الشرطة الهولندية من تقفي أثر البدلة
by an RFID chip that was sewn in the suit.
بفضل رقاقة إلكترونية كانت مخيطة في البدلة.
So they were then able to tell
حينئذِ كان بإمكانهم القول
that both wetsuits were bought by the same customer at the same time,
أن البذلتين إشتراهما شخص واحد في نفس الوقت
October 7, 2014,
يوم 7 أكتوبر 2014،
in the French city of Calais by the English Channel.
بمدينة كاليه الفرنسية على القناة الإنجليزية.
But this was all they were able to figure out.
لكن كان هذا كل ما تمكنوا من إيجاده.
The customer paid cash.
إشترى الشخص البذلتين نقدا.
There was no surveillance footage from the shop.
لم يكن للمتجرأي تصوير أمني.
So it became a cold case.
فأصبحت قضية عالقة.
We heard this story,
سمعنا بهذه القضية،
and it triggered me and my colleague, photographer Tomm Christiansen,
أثارتني و أثارت زميلي المصور توم كريسنسن.
and we of course had the obvious question: who were these people?
و بالطبع، كان تساؤلنا بديهيا: من كانا هاذين الشخصين؟
At the time, I'd barely heard about Calais,
في ذلك الوقت، لم أكن أعرف كثيرا عن كاليه،
but it took about two or three seconds to figure out
و لكن استغرق ذلك حوالي ثانيتين أو ثلاثة ثواني لمعرفة ذلك
Calais is basically known for two things.
تُعرف كاليه أساسا بأمرين.
It's the spot in continental Europe closest to Britain,
هي المكان الأقرب من بريطانيا في قارة أوروبا
and a lot of migrants and refugees are staying in this camp
والكثير من المهاجرين واللاجئين يقيمون في هذا المخيم
and are trying desperately to cross over to Britain.
و يحاولون العبور إلى بريطانيا بلا جدوى.
And right there was a plausible theory about the identity of the two people,
وكانت هناك نظرية معقولة حول هوية هذين الشخصين،
and the police made this theory as well.
وضعت الشرطة نفس النظرية.
Because if you or I or anybody else with a firm connection to Europe
لأنه إذا غبت عن سواحل فرنسا أنت أو أنا أو أي شخص
goes missing off the coast of France, people would just know.
ولديك علاقة قوية بأوروبا سيعلم الأشخاص.
Your friends or family would report you missing,
أصدقائك أوعائلتك سيُبلغون عن فقدانك،
the police would come search for you, the media would know,
ستبحث عنك الشرطة، وسيعلم الإعلام،
and there would be pictures of you on lampposts.
وتُلصّق صورتك في الشارع على أعمدة المصابيح.
It's difficult to disappear without a trace.
من الصعب الغياب بدون أي أثر.
But if you just fled the war in Syria,
ولكن إذا كنت تفر من الحرب في سوريا،
and your family, if you have any family left,
وعائلتك، إذا بقي لك أفراد من عائلتك،
don't necessarily know where you are,
لا تعرف حتما أين أنت،
and you're staying here illegally
وستقيم هنا بطريقة غير شرعيّة
amongst thousands of others who come and go every day.
بين آلاف الآخرين يأتون ويذهبون كل يوم.
Well, if you disappear one day, nobody will notice.
طبعا، إذا اختفيت يوما فلن يلاحظ ذلك أحد.
The police won't come search for you because nobody knows you're gone.
لن تبحث عنك الشرطة لأنه لا أحد يدري أنك رحلت.
And this is what happened to Shadi Omar Kataf
وهذا ما حدث للسوريان
and Mouaz Al Balkhi from Syria.
شادي عمر خطاف ومعاذ البلخي.
Me and Tomm went to Calais for the first time in April this year,
ذهبت مع توم إلى كاليه لأول مرة في شهر أبريل هذه السنة،
and after three months of investigation, we were able to tell the story
وبعد ثلاثة أشهر من التحقيق، تمكنا من رواية القصة
about how these two young men fled the war in Syria,
حول كيفية فرار هذين الشابين من الحرب في سوريا،
ended up stuck in Calais,
لينته بهما المطاف إلى كاليه،
bought wetsuits and drowned in what seems to have been an attempt
إشتريا بذلتي غوص فغرقا فيما يبدوا أنها كانت محاولة
to swim across the English Channel in order to reach England.
عبور القناة الإنجليزية سباحة للوصول إلى انجلترا.
It is a story about the fact that everybody has a name,
هذه قصة تدلّ على أن كلّ شخص له إسم،
everybody has a story, everybody is someone.
كل شخص له قصّة، كل شخص هو إنسان.
But it is also a story about what it's like to be a refugee in Europe today.
و لكن هي كذلك قصة عن حالة اللاجئيين في أوروبا اليوم.
So this is where we started our search.
فهذا هو الموضوع الذي بدأنا تحقيقنا حوله.
This is in Calais.
هذا في كاليه.
Right now, between 3,500 and 5,000 people are living here
حاليا، ما بين 3500 و5000 شخصا يعيش هنا
under horrible conditions.
في ظروف مروعة.
It has been dubbed the worst refugee camp in Europe.
تم تعريفه بأسوء مخيم للاجئيين بأوروبا،
Limited access to food, limited access to water,
محدودية الحصول على الأكل، محدودية الحصول على الماء،
limited access to health care.
محدودية الحصول على رعاية صحية.
Disease and infections are widespread.
الأمراض والعدوى منتشرة في مختلف أرجاء المخيم
And they're all stuck here because they're trying to get to England
وعلقوا هناك جميعهم لأنهم يحاولون الوصول إلى إنجلترا
in order to claim asylum.
لطلب اللجوء.
And they do that by hiding in the back of trucks headed for the ferry,
وذلك بالإختباء وراء شاحنة تمر بالمعبر،
or the Eurotunnel,
أو عبر النفق الأوروبي،
or they sneak inside the tunnel terminal at night
أو بالتسلل داخل محطة النفق ليلا
to try to hide on the trains.
لمحاولة الإختباء بالقطارات.
Most want to go to Britain because they know the language,
معظمهم يرغبون في الوصول إلى بريطانيا لأنهم يعرفون اللغة،
and so they figure it would be easier to restart their lives from there.
ويجدون أنه من السهل بدء حياتهم من هناك.
They want to work, they want to study,
يريدون العمل و الدراسة،
they want to be able to continue their lives.
يريدون فرصة لمواصلة عيش حياتهم.
A lot of these people are highly educated and skilled workers.
والكثير منهم عمال متعلّمون جيّدا ولديهم مهارات هائلة.
If you go to Calais and talk to refugees, you'll meet lawyers, politicians,
إذا تحدثت مع اللاجئين في كاليه فستلتقي بمحامين وسياسيين،
engineers, graphic designers, farmers, soldiers.
ومهندسين ومصممي طباعة ومزارعين وجنود.
You've got the whole spectrum.
تجدون كل الأصناف.
But who all of these people are
ولكن عادة ما تضيع هوية هؤلاء الأشخاص
usually gets lost in the way we talk about refugees and migrants,
في طريقة تحدثنا عن اللاجئين والمهاجرين،
because we usually do that in statistics.
لأننا عادة ما نستعمل الإحصاءات لذلك.
So you have 60 million refugees globally.
فلدينا 60 مليون لاجئ في العالم.
About half a million have made the crossing
هذه السنة، حوالي نصف مليون شخص قد عبر
over the Mediterranean into Europe so far this year,
البحر الأبيض المتوسط إلى أوروبا حتى الآن،
and roughly 4,000 are staying in Calais.
وتقريبا 4000 منهم مقيمون بكاليه.
But these are numbers,
لكن هذه مجرّد أرقام،
and the numbers don't say anything about who these people are,
ولا تدل هذه الأرقام على هويّة هؤلاء الأشخاص،
where they came from, or why they're here.
من أين أتوا أو لماذا هم هنا.
And first, I want to tell you about one of them.
أولا، أودّ أن أخبركم عن أحدهم.
This is 22-year-old Mouaz Al Balkhi from Syria.
هذا معاذ البلخي السوري والبالغ من العمر 22 سنة.
We first heard about him after being in Calais the first time
سمعنا عنه عندما كنا أوّل مرّة بكاليه
looking for answers to the theory of the two dead bodies.
نبحث عن إجابات لنظريّة الجثتين.
And after a while, we heard this story
وبعد مدّة، سمعنا هذه القصّة
about a Syrian man who was living in Bradford in England,
عن رجل سوري كان يعيش في برادفورد في إنجلترا،
and had been desperately searching for his nephew Mouaz for months.
وكان يبحث بيأس عن إبن أخيه معاذ لمدّة أشهر.
And it turned out the last time anybody had heard anything from Mouaz
واتضح في المرّة الأخيرة بأنّه هناك شخص ما قد سمع شيئا عن معاذ
was October 7, 2014.
في 7 أكتوبر 2014.
That was the same date the wetsuits were bought.
كان ذلك نفس التاريخ الذي وجدت فيه البدلتين.
So we flew over there and we met the uncle
لذلك ذهبنا إلى هناك وقابلنا العمّ
and we did DNA samples of him,
وقمنا بتحليل عينات من حمضه النووي،
and later on got additional DNA samples from Mouaz's closest relative
ثم قمنا بتحليل عينات إضافيّة لأقرباء معاذ
who now lives in Jordan.
الذين يعيشون حاليّا بالأردن.
The analysis concluded
وأجزمت التحاليل
the body who was found in a wetsuit on a beach in the Netherlands
بأن الجثة التي وُجدت ببدلة الغوص على شاطئ هولاندا
was actually Mouaz Al Balkhi.
كانت في الواقع لمعاذ البلخي.
And while we were doing all this investigation,
وبينما كنا نقوم بكلّ هذا التحقيق،
we got to know Mouaz's story.
تمكّنا من معرفة قصّة معاذ.
He was born in the Syrian capital of Damascus in 1991.
وُلد بالعاصمة السوريّة دمشق في سنة 1991.
He was raised in a middle class family,
ونشأ في عائلة من الطبقة المتوسّطة،
and his father in the middle there is a chemical engineer
وكان والده مهندس كيميائي
who spent 11 years in prison for belonging to the political opposition in Syria.
قضّى 11 سنة في السجن بتهمة الإنتماء إلى المعارضة السياسيّة بسوريا.
While his father was in prison,
بينما كان والده في السجن،
Mouaz took responsibility and he cared for his three sisters.
أخذ معاذ مسؤوليّة أخواته الثلاثة على عاتقه.
They said he was that kind of guy.
وقالوا أنه كان قادراً علي تحمل المسؤولية
Mouaz studied to become an electrical engineer
درس معاز لكي يُصبح مهندس كهربائي
at the University of Damascus.
بجامعة دمشق.
So a couple of years into the Syrian war,
إذن لمدّة سنتين خلال الحرب السوريّة،
the family fled Damascus and went to the neighboring country, Jordan.
فرت العائلة من دمشق إلى بلد مجاور وهو الأردن.
Their father had problems finding work in Jordan,
واجهت والدهم عدة مشاكل للعثور على عمل بالأردن،
and Mouaz could not continue his studies,
ولم يكن معاذ قادرا على إنهاء دراسته،
so he figured, "OK, the best thing I can do to help my family
لذا قال، "حسنا، أحسن شيء أقوم به لكي أساعد عائلتي
would be to go somewhere where I can finish my studies
هو الذهاب إلى مكان ما حيث يُمكنني إنهاء درستي
and find work."
وإيجاد عمل."
So he goes to Turkey.
لذا ذهب إلى تركيا.
In Turkey, he's not accepted at a university,
في تركيا، لم يتم قبوله بالجامعة،
and once he had left Jordan as a refugee, he was not allowed to reenter.
وحين مغادرته للأردن كلاجئ لم يُسمح له بالرجوع مجددا.
So then he decides to head for the UK,
حينها قرّر التوجّه إلى المملكة المتّحدة،
where his uncle lives.
حيث يقطن عمّه.
He makes it into Algeria, walks into Libya,
ذهب إلى الجزائر ثمّ توجّه إلى ليبيا،
pays a people smuggler to help him with the crossing into Italy by boat,
دفع مبلغا لمهرّبي الأشخاص خلسة لمساعدته على عبور حدود إيطاليا
and from there on he heads to Dunkirk,
بالقارب ثم من هناك التوجّه إلى دونكيرك،
the city right next to Calais by the English Channel.
بالقرب من كاليه، بجانب قنال البحر الإنجليزي.
We know he made at least 12 failed attempts to cross the English Channel
لقد قام على الأقل ب12 محاولة فاشلة لعبور قنال البحر الإنجليزي.
by hiding in a truck.
عن طريق الإختباء في شاحنة.
But at some point, he must have given up all hope.
ولكن في مرحلة ما، انقطع الأمل.
The last night we know he was alive,
في الليلة الماضية التي علمنا فيها أنه حيّ،
he spent at a cheap hotel close to the train station in Dunkirk.
قضّاها في أحد الفنادق الرخيصة على مقربة من محطة القطار في دونكريك.
We found his name in the records, and he seems to have stayed there alone.
وجدنا إسمه في السجلّات، ويبدو أنه كان بمفرده.
The day after, he went into Calais, entered a sports shop
وفي اليوم التالي، ذهب إلى كاليه، دخل إلى محلّ رياضي
a couple of minutes before 8 o'clock in the evening,
بضعة دقائق قبل 8 مساءً،
along with Shadi Kataf.
مع شادي قطاف.
They both bought wetsuits,
اشترى كلّ منهما بدلة غوص،
and the woman in the shop
والسيّدة الموجودة بالمحلّ
was the last person we know of to have seen them alive.
هي آخر شخص نعرفه شاهده على قيد الحياة.
We have tried to figure out where Shadi met Mouaz,
حاولنا معرفة المكان الذي تقابل فيه شادي ومعاذ،
but we weren't able to do that.
ولكن لم نتمكّن من ذلك.
But they do have a similar story.
ولكن قصصهما متشابهة.
We first heard about Shadi after a cousin of his, living in Germany,
سمعنا في الأول عن شادي من إبن عمّه يعيش في ألمانيا،
had read an Arabic translation of the story made of Mouaz on Facebook.
والذي قرأ ترجمة باللغة العربيّة لقصّة معاذ على موقع فيسبوك.
So we got in touch with him.
لذا اتصلنا به.
Shadi, a couple of years older than Mouaz,
شادي أكبر من معاذ بسنتين،
was also raised in Damascus.
تربّى أيضا بدمشق.
He was a working kind of guy.
ولقد كان من النوع العامل.
He ran a tire repair shop and later worked in a printing company.
كان يدير ورشة لإصلاح الإطارات ثم عمل بشركة طباعة.
He lived with his extended family,
عاش مع عائلته متعدّدة الأفراد،
but their house got bombed early in the war.
ولكن تم قصف منزلهم خلال الحرب.
So the family fled to an area of Damascus known as Camp Yarmouk.
لذا سافرت العائلة إلى منطقة بدمشق معروفة باسم مخيم اليرموك.
Yarmouk is being described as the worst place to live
تُعرف اليرموك كأسوأ منطقة للعيش بها
on planet Earth.
على وجه الأرض.
They've been bombed by the military, they've been besieged,
لقد تم قصفها من قبل الجيش، وتمت مُحاصرتها،
they've been stormed by ISIS
وتم إقتحامها من قبل تنظيم الدولة الإسلامية
and they've been cut off from supplies for years.
وتمّ منع حصولهم على الإمدادات لمدّة سنوات.
There was a UN official who visited last year,
وزار مسؤول من الأمم المتحدة تلك المنطقة العام الماضي،
and he said, "They ate all the grass so there was no grass left."
وصرّح، "لقد أكلوا كلّ العشب، لذلك لم يعد يوجد عشب."
Out of a population of 150,000,
من بين 150.000 ساكنا،
only 18,000 are believed to still be left in Yarmouk.
تبقّى فقط 18.000 شخص باليرموك.
Shadi and his sisters got out.
خرج شادي وشقيقاته من تلك المنطقة.
The parents are still stuck inside.
بينما ما يزال والديه عالقان هناك.
So Shadi and one of his sisters, they fled to Libya.
إذن فر شادي وإحدى شقيقاته إلى ليبيا.
This was after the fall of Gaddafi,
كان هذا بعد سقوط القذافي،
but before Libya turned into full-blown civil war.
ولكن قبل أن تتحوّل ليبيا إلى حرب أهليّة شاملة.
And in this last remaining sort of stability in Libya,
وفي خضم هذا الإستقرار المُتبقّي بليبيا،
Shadi took up scuba diving, and he seemed to spend most of his time underwater.
اختار شادي الغوص، وبدا أنه يقضي مُعظم وقته تحت الماء.
He fell completely in love with the ocean,
لقد تولّدت قصّة حبّ بينه وبين البحر،
so when he finally decided that he could no longer be in Libya,
لذا عندما قرّر أخيرا بأنه لم يعد يستطيع البقاء في ليبيا،
late August 2014,
في أوغسطس الماضي 2014،
he hoped to find work as a diver when he reached Italy.
وكان له أمل في العثور على عمل كغوّاص عند وصوله إلى إيطاليا.
Reality was not that easy.
الواقع لم يكن بتلك السهولة.
We don't know much about his travels
ليس لدينا معرفة كبيرة عن رحلاته
because he had a hard time communicating with his family,
لأنه كان يواجه صعوبة في الإتصال بعائلته،
but we do know that he struggled.
ولكننا لا نعرف بأنه واجه وقتا عصيبا.
And by the end of September,
وبحلول نهاية سبتمبر،
he was living on the streets somewhere in France.
كان يعيش في الشوارع بمكان ما بفرنسا.
On October 7, he calls his cousin in Belgium,
في 7 أكتوبر، اتصل بابن عمّه في بلجيكا،
and explains his situation.
وفسّر له وضعه.
He said, "I'm in Calais. I need you to come get my backpack and my laptop.
قال "أنا بكاليه، أنا أحتاج إليك لتأتي وتأخذ معك حقيبتي وحاسوبي.
I can't afford to pay the people smugglers to help me with the crossing to Britain,
لا أستطيع توفير المال لأدفعه لمهرّبي الأشخاص ليساعدوني في العبور
but I will go buy a wetsuit and I will swim."
إلى بريطانيا ولكنني سأشتري بدلة غطس وآذهب إلى هناك سباحة."
His cousin, of course, tried to warn him not to,
ولقد حاول إبن عمّه بالطبع تحذيره من القيام بذلك،
but Shadi's battery on the phone went flat,
ولكن بطاريّة هاتف شادي قد نفذ شحنها،
and his phone was never switched on again.
ولم يشتغل هاتفه مرة ثانية.
What was left of Shadi was found nearly three months later,
لقد تم إيجاد ما بقي من شادي ما يقارب 3 أشهر بعد ذلك،
800 kilometers away
على بعد 800 كم
in a wetsuit on a beach in Norway.
ببدلة غطس على شاطئ النرويج.
He's still waiting for his funeral in Norway,
ما يزالون ينتظرون جنازته بالنرويج،
and none of his family will be able to attend.
ولن يستطيع أي فرد من عائلته الحضور.
Many may think that the story about Shadi and Mouaz
ربما يعتقد العديد منكم أن قصّة شادي ومعاذ تتمحور
is a story about death,
حول الموت،
but I don't agree.
ولكنني لا أتفق معكم في ذلك.
To me, this is a story about two questions that I think we all share:
بالنسبة لي، تتمحور هذه القصّة حول سؤالين واللذان أعتقد أنها يشملانا جميعا:
what is a better life,
ماهي أحسن حياة،
and what am I willing to do to achieve it?
وما الذي سأقوم به لتحقيق ذلك؟
And to me, and probably a lot of you,
وبالنسبة لي، وحتما بالنسبة للكثير منكم،
a better life would mean
حياة أفضل بالضرورة تعني
being able to do more of what we think of as meaningful,
القدرة على القيام بما نعتقد أنه ذو معنى بالنسبة لنا،
whether that be spending more time with your family and friends,
سواء كان ذلك قضاء مزيد من الوقت مع عائلتك وأصدقائك،
travel to an exotic place,
السفر إلى مكان مدهش،
or just getting money to buy that cool new device
أو الحصول على مال لشراء جهاز جديد
or a pair of new sneakers.
أو حذاء رياضي جديد.
And this is all within our reach pretty easily.
وهذا كلّه في متناولنا وبكلّ سهولة.
But if you are fleeing a war zone,
ولكن إن كنت فارّا من منطقة بها حرب،
the answers to those two questions are dramatically different.
الإجابات على هذين السؤالين تختلف بشكل كبير.
A better life is a life in safety.
حياة أفضل هي العيش في أمان.
It's a life in dignity.
إنها الحياة بكرامة.
A better life means not having your house bombed,
حياة أفضل بمعنى عدم تعرّض منزلك للقصف،
not fearing being kidnapped.
عدم الخوف من أن يتم إختطافك.
It means being able to send your children to school,
بمعنى أن تكون لك القدرة على إرسال أبنائك إلى المدرسة،
go to university,
أو الذهاب إلى الجامعة،
or just find work to be able to provide for yourself and the ones you love.
أو فقط القدرة على توفير عمل لنفسك أو لأشخاص تحبهم.
A better life would be a future of some possibilities
حياة أفضل هي مستقبل مع بعض الإحتمالات
compared to nearly none,
مقارنة بلا شيء،
and that's a strong motivation.
وهذا دافع قويّ.
And I have no trouble imagining
وليس لدي أي مشكلة في تخيّل
that after spending weeks or even months
بعد قضاء أسابيع أو حتى أشهر
as a second-grade citizen,
كمواطن من الدرجة الثانية،
living on the streets or in a horrible makeshift camp
العيش في الشوارع أو في مخيم مؤقّت مخيف
with a stupid, racist name like "The Jungle,"
مع حمل إسم غبيّ مثل "الغابة"،
most of us would be willing to do just about anything.
العديد منا مستعد للقيام بأي شيء.
If I could ask Shadi and Mouaz
إذا كنت قادرا على سؤال شادي ومعاذ
the second they stepped into the freezing waters of the English Channel,
عن اللحظة التي اقتربا فيها من الماء البارد جدا لمياه القنال الإنجليزي
they would probably say, "This is worth the risk,"
سيجيبانني حتما، "هذا يستحق المخاطرة"،
because they could no longer see any other option.
لأنه لن يكون لديهما خيار آخر.
And that's desperation,
وهذا هو اليأس،
but that's the reality of living as a refugee in Western Europe in 2015.
ولكن هذه حقيقة العيش كلاجئ في أوروبا الغربية في سنة 2015.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Anders.
برونو جيوزاني: شكرا لك أندرس.
This is Tomm Christiansen,
هذا توم كرستيانسن،
who took most of the pictures you have seen and they've done reporting together.
وهو من قام بالتقاط جميع الصور التي شاهدتوها ولقد قاما بالتقرير معا.
Tomm, you two have been back to Calais recently.
توم، أنتم الإثنين رجعتم إلى كاليه مؤخّرا.
This was the third trip.
كانت هذه الرحلة الثالثة.
It was after the publication of the article.
كانت بعد نشر المقال.
What has changed? What have you seen there?
ما الذي تغيّر؟ ما الذي رأيته هناك؟
Tomm Christiansen: The first time we were in Calais,
توم كرستيانسن: أوّل مرة كنا في كاليه،
it was about 1,500 refugees there.
كان هناك ما يقارب 1500 لاجئ.
They had a difficult time, but they were positive, they had hope.
واجهوا وقتا صعبا، ولكنهّم كانوا مفعمين بالإيجابية، كان لهم أمل.
The last time, the camp has grown, maybe four or five thousand people.
وخلال المرة الماضية، شهد المخيّم توسّعا، قرابة أربعة أو خمسة آلاف شخص.
It seemed more permanent, NGOs have arrived,
بدا الأمر دائما، إلتحقت بالمكان المنظمات غير الحكوميّة،
a small school has opened.
وتمّ تشييد مدرسة.
But the thing is that the refugees have stayed for a longer time,
ولكن بقي اللاجئون لمدّة أطول،
and the French government has managed to seal off the borders better,
وقامت الحكومة الفرنسية بغلق الحدود بشكل أفضل،
so now The Jungle is growing,
والآن "الغابة" تكبر أكثر،
along with the despair and hopelessness among the refugees.
مع تفشّي اليأس والإحباط بين صفوف اللاجئين.
BG: Are you planning to go back? And continue the reporting?
برونو جيوزاني: هل تخطّط للعودة؟ وإكمال التقرير؟
TC: Yes.
توم كرستيانسن: نعم.
BG: Anders, I'm a former journalist,
برونو جيوزاني: أندرس، أنا صحفي سابق،
and to me, it's amazing that in the current climate
وبالنسبة لي، إنه من المدهش في ظلّ المناخ الحالي
of slashing budgets and publishers in crisis,
والعجز المالي، وأزمة دار النشر،
Dagbladet has consented so many resources for this story,
موافقة داجبلاديت على توفير الكثير من الموارد لهذه القصّة،
which tells a lot about newspapers taking the responsibility,
وهو ما يدلّ على تحمّل الصحف للمسؤوليّة،
but how did you sell it to your editors?
ولكن كيف قمت ببيعه للمحررين الخاصين بك؟
Anders Fjellberg: It wasn't easy at first,
أندرس فجلبرغ: لم يكن ذلك سهلا في الأول،
because we weren't able to know what we actually could figure out.
لأننا لم نكن نعرف ما الذي نبحث عنه.
As soon as it became clear
وبمجرّد أن أصبح ذلك واضحا
that we actually could be able to identify who the first one was,
حتّى تمكّنا من تحديد من كان الأول،
we basically got the message that we could do whatever we wanted,
لقد تلقينا في الأساس رسالة بأنه يمكننا القيام بما نشاء،
just travel wherever you need to go, do whatever you need to do,
السفر عندما تريدون ذلك، القيام بما عليكم القيام به،
just get this done.
فقط أنهوا القيام بذلك.
BG: That's an editor taking responsibility.
برونو جيوزاني: هذا محرّر يتحمّل المسؤوليّة.
The story, by the way, has been translated and published
على فكرة، هذه القصّة تمّت ترجمتها ونشرها
across several European countries, and certainly will continue to do.
في مختلف أنحاء الدول الأوروبية وبالتأكيد سنواصل القيام بذلك.
And we want to read the updates from you. Thank you Anders. Thank you Tomm.
ونريد قراءة آخر التحديثات من عندكم. شكرا لك أندرس. شكرا لك توم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )